<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-01-20T12:40:58-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Dana C. Ernst</title><subtitle>Mathematics, Teaching, &amp; Technology</subtitle><author><name>Dana C. Ernst</name></author><entry><title type="html">Quote by Marcus Aurelius</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/marcus-aurelius-quote/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quote by Marcus Aurelius" /><published>2018-01-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-01-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/marcus-aurelius-quote</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/marcus-aurelius-quote/">&lt;p&gt;I recently listened to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.powercompanyclimbing.com/blog/2017/11/6/episode-64-fixed-vs-growth-mindset-with-trevor-ragan-from-trainugly&quot;&gt;Episode 64&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.powercompanyclimbing.com/podcast/&quot;&gt;The Power Company Podcast&lt;/a&gt;. In this episode, the host interviews &lt;a href=&quot;http://trainugly.com/trevor-ragan/&quot;&gt;Trevor Ragan&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://trainugly.com&quot;&gt;TrainUgly&lt;/a&gt; and the topic of discussion is fixed versus growth mindset. For an introduction to growth mindset, a good place to start is the post I wrote for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://maateachingtidbits.blogspot.com&quot;&gt;Teaching Tidbits Blog&lt;/a&gt; called &lt;a href=&quot;http://maateachingtidbits.blogspot.com/2017/11/the-role-of-failure-and-struggle-in.html&quot;&gt;The Role of Failure and Struggle in the Mathematics Classroom&lt;/a&gt;. At the end of the podcast, Ragan suggests some further reading.  One of those books is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Obstacle-Way-Timeless-Turning-Triumph/dp/1591846358&quot;&gt;The Obstacle is the Way: The Timeless Art of Turning Trials into Triumph&lt;/a&gt; by Ryan Holiday, which I recently started reading.  The beginning of this book contains the following quote by Roman emperor &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcus_Aurelius&quot;&gt;Marcus Aurelius&lt;/a&gt; that embraces obstacles and discourages the fear of failure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impediment to action advances action. What stands in the way becomes the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;Marcus Aurelius&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Dana Ernst</name></author><category term="productive struggle" /><category term="productive failure" /><category term="growth mindset" /><category term="Marcus Aurelius" /><category term="quote" /><summary type="html">I recently listened to Episode 64 of The Power Company Podcast. In this episode, the host interviews Trevor Ragan from TrainUgly and the topic of discussion is fixed versus growth mindset. For an introduction to growth mindset, a good place to start is the post I wrote for the Teaching Tidbits Blog called The Role of Failure and Struggle in the Mathematics Classroom. At the end of the podcast, Ragan suggests some further reading. One of those books is The Obstacle is the Way: The Timeless Art of Turning Trials into Triumph by Ryan Holiday, which I recently started reading. The beginning of this book contains the following quote by Roman emperor Marcus Aurelius that embraces obstacles and discourages the fear of failure:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quote by Bruce Lee</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bruce-lee-quote/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quote by Bruce Lee" /><published>2017-12-31T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-12-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bruce-lee-quote</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bruce-lee-quote/">&lt;p&gt;Here’s a great quote about failure by Chinese-American martial arts master and actor &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bruce_Lee&quot;&gt;Bruce Lee&lt;/a&gt; (1940–1973):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t fear failure.  Not failure, but low aim, is the crime. In great attempts it is glorious even to fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;Bruce Lee&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This quote appears on page 121 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Bruce-Lee-Striking-Thoughts-Library/dp/0804834717&quot;&gt;Striking Thoughts: Bruce Lee’s Wisdom for Daily Living&lt;/a&gt;.  For more great quotes, check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Bruce_Lee&quot;&gt;Wikiquote page for Bruce Lee&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dana Ernst</name></author><category term="productive struggle" /><category term="productive failure" /><category term="growth mindset" /><category term="Bruce Lee" /><category term="quote" /><summary type="html">Here’s a great quote about failure by Chinese-American martial arts master and actor Bruce Lee (1940–1973):</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quote by Henri Poincaré</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poincare-quote/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quote by Henri Poincaré" /><published>2017-11-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-11-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poincare-quote</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poincare-quote/">&lt;p&gt;I love the following quote by French mathematician Henri Poincaré (1854-1912).  I’m not sure what the original source is, but it is cited in the introduction to &lt;em&gt;The Divine Proportion&lt;/em&gt; (1970) by H.E. Huntley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mathematician does not study pure mathematics because it is useful; he studies it because he delights in it, and he delights in it because it is beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;Henri Poincaré&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Dana Ernst</name></author><category term="math" /><category term="mathematics" /><category term="Henri Poincaré" /><category term="beauty" /><category term="quote" /><summary type="html">I love the following quote by French mathematician Henri Poincaré (1854-1912). I’m not sure what the original source is, but it is cited in the introduction to The Divine Proportion (1970) by H.E. Huntley.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Students’ Favorite Problems from Spring 2017</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/students-favorite-problems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Students' Favorite Problems from Spring 2017" /><published>2017-06-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-06-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/students-favorite-problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/students-favorite-problems/">&lt;p&gt;A few semesters ago we launched a course for mathematics majors, called MAT 220: Introduction to Mathematical Reasoning. The focus of the course is on reasoning and communication through problem solving and written mathematical arguments in order to provide students with more experience and training early in their university studies. The goal is for the students to work on interesting yet challenging multi-step problems that require almost zero background knowledge. The hope is that students will develop (or at least move in the direction of) the habits of mind of a mathematician. The problem solving of the type in this course is a fundamental component of mathematics that receives little focused attention elsewhere in most mathematics programs. I love teaching this course!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past semester I taught the course for the second time.  You can find the syllabus, list of problems, etc. for the Spring 2017 semester by going &lt;a href=&quot;https://dcernst.github.io/teaching/mat220s17/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. On the students’ final exam, I asked them which problem was their favorite from the semester.  Below is the list of problems that they mentioned including the number of votes that each received. The level of difficulty of the problems covers the spectrum.  Some of these are not easy. Have fun playing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(6 votes; several students commented that their favorite part about this problem was how excited the student was that solved it) An overfull prison has decided to terminate some prisoners. The jailer comes up with a game for selecting who gets terminated. Here is his scheme. 10 prisoners are to be lined up all facing the same direction. On the back of each prisoner’s head, the jailer places either a black or a red dot. Each prisoner can only see the color of the dot for all of the prisoners in front of them and the prisoners do not know how many of each color there are. The jailer may use all black dots, or perhaps he uses 3 red and 7 black, but the prisoners do not know. The jailer tells the prisoners that if a prisoner can guess the color of the dot on the back of their head, they will live, but if they guess incorrectly, they will be terminated. The jailer will call on them in order starting at the back of the line. Before lining up the prisoners and placing the dots, the jailer allows the prisoners 5 minutes to come up with a plan that will maximize their survival. What plan can the prisoners devise that will maximize the number of prisoners that survive? Some more info: each prisoner can hear the answer of the prisoner behind them and they will know whether the prisoner behind them has lived or died. Also, each prisoner can only respond with the word “black” or “red.” Now, suppose that there are 11 prisoners. Describe a strategy for maximizing the number of prisoners that will live. What if there are $n$ prisoners?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(4 votes) Four prisoners are making plans to escape from jail. Their current plan requires them to cross a narrow bridge in the dark that has no handrail. In order to successfully cross the bridge, they must use a flashlight.  However, they only have a single flashlight.  To complicate matters, at most two people can be on the bridge at the same time.  So, they will need to make multiple trips across the bridge, returning the flashlight back to the first side of the bridge by having someone walk it back.  Unfortunately, they can’t throw the flashlight.  It takes 1, 2, 5, and 10 minutes for prisoner $A$, prisoner $B$, prisoner $C$, and prisoner $D$ to cross the bridge and when two prisoners are walking together with the flashlight, it takes the time of the slower prisoner.  What is the minimum total amount of time it takes all four prisoners to get across the bridge?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(3 votes; we encountered several variations of this problem) Suppose you have 12 coins, all identical in appearance and weight except for one that is either heavier or lighter than the other 11 coins. What is the minimum number of weighing one must do with a two-pan scale in order to identify the counterfeit? Now, suppose you have $n$ coins. For which $n$ is it possible to devise a procedure for identifying the counterfeit coin in only 3 weighings with a two-pan scale?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(3 votes) 100 prisoners are isolated in individual jail cells with no way to communicate. They are currently serving life sentences.  Due to an overcrowded prison, the jailer decides to offer the prisoners the following deal. There is a room with nothing in it except a light switch (that starts in the off position). At random, the jailer will escort a single prisoner into the room with the light switch. After 5 seconds, the jailer will escort the prisoner back to his/her jail cell. The jailer will repeat this over and over again.  He tells each of the prisoners that if one of the prisoners can indicate when every prisoner has been in the room with the light switch at least once, he will let all the prisoners go.  However, if a prisoner erroneously states that each prisoner has been in the room with the light switch, then all the prisoners will be executed.  Before beginning, the jailer gets all 100 prisoners together and gives them 5 minutes to come up with a plan.  What should their plan be?  It’s important to note that the jailer is choosing prisoners at random to take in the room.  That is, by chance, the same prisoner may be escorted to the room several times in a row.  Also, your task is to devise a scheme for the prisoners to communicate with the light switch.  You shouldn’t bother searching for other ways for the prisoners to communicate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(2 votes; we encountered several variations of this problem) A soul swapping machine swaps the souls inside two bodies placed in the machine. Soon after the invention of the machine an unforeseen limitation is discovered: swapping only works on a pair of bodies once. Souls get more and more homesick as they spend time in another body and if a soul is not returned to its original body after a few days, it will kill its current host. Bart (B), Lisa (L), Homer (H), Marge (M), and Ned (N) were involved in a soul-swapping bonanza that resulted in Bart’s soul being Lisa’s body, Lisa’s soul being in Homer’s body, Homer’s body being in Marge’s body, Marge’s soul in Ned’s body, and Ned’s soul being in Bart’s body.  Thankfully, Krusty the Clown (K) and Santa’s Little Help (S) never utilized the machine and are available to help put everyone’s soul back in the appropriate body.  Find a way to return all the souls to their respective owner.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(1 vote; see the discussion of Problem 86 on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dcernst.github.io/teaching/mat220s17/journal/&quot;&gt;class journal&lt;/a&gt; for Monday, May 1) The first vote counts of the papal conclave resulted in 33 votes each for candidates A and B and 34 votes for candidate C. The cardinals then discussed the candidates in pairs. In the second round each pair of cardinals with differing first votes changed their votes to the third candidate they did not vote for in the first round. The new vote counts were 16, 17 and 67. They were about to start the smoke signal when Cardinal Ordinal shouted “wait”. What was his reason?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(1 vote) Recent archaeological work on Mars shows a number of sites, each site containing a large mound of white spheres, each about the size of a tennis ball. Each ball contains a jewel. The jewels come in many different colors, but at each site, strictly more than half of the spheres contain jewels of the same color. When two balls are brought together, they both glow white if their internal jewels are the same color; otherwise, no glow. You have recently stumbled on a cache of 13 spheres. In how few tests can you find a sphere that you are certain holds a jewel of the majority color?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(1 vote) A certain fast-food chain sells a product called “nuggets” in boxes of $6, 9$, and $20$. A number $n$ is called &lt;em&gt;nuggetable&lt;/em&gt; if one can buy exactly $n$ nuggets by buying some number of boxes. For example, $21$ is nuggetable since you can buy two boxes of six and one box of nine to get 21. Here are the first few nuggetable numbers: $6, 9, 12, 15, 18, 20, 21, 24, 26, 27,\ldots$
and here are the first few non-nuggetable numbers: $1,2,3,4,5,7,8,10,11,13,\ldots$. What is the largest non-nuggetable number?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(1 vote) A signed permutation of the numbers 1 through $n$ is a fixed arrangement of the numbers 1 through $n$, where each number can be either be positive or negative. For example, $(-2,1, -4,5,3)$ is a signed permutation of the numbers 1 through 5.  In this case, think of positive numbers as being right-side-up and negative numbers as being upside-down. A &lt;em&gt;reversal&lt;/em&gt; of a signed permutation is the act of performing a 180-degree rotation to some consecutive subsequence of the permutation. That is, a reversal swaps the order of a subsequence of numbers while changing the sign of each number in the subsequence. Performing a reversal to a signed permutation results in a new signed permutation. For example, if we perform a reversal on the second, third, and fourth entries in $(-2,1,-4,5,3)$, we obtain $(-2,-5,4,-1,3)$.  The &lt;em&gt;reversal distance&lt;/em&gt; of a signed permutation of 1 through $n$ is the minimum number of reversals required to transform the given signed permutation into $(1,2,\ldots,n)$. It turns out that the reversal distance of $(3,1,6,5,-2,4)$ is 5. Find a sequence of 5 reversals that transforms $(3,1,6,5,-2,4)$ into $(1,2,3,4,5,6)$.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(1 vote) My Uncle Robert owns a stable with 25 race horses.  He wants to know which three are the fastest.  He owns a race track that can accommodate five horses at a time. What is the minimum number of races required to determine the fastest three horses?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(1 vote) Each integer on the number line is colored with exactly one of three possible colors, red, green, or blue, according to the following two rules:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;(Rule 1) The negative of a red number must be colored blue;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;(Rule 2) The sum of two blue numbers (not necessarily distinct) must be colored red.
Using this information, determine all possible colorings of the integers that satisfy these rules.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(1 vote) Annie, Bob, and Cristy are sitting by a campfire when Cristy announces that she is thinking of a 3-digit number.  She then tells Annie and Bob that the number she is thinking of is one of the following: $515, 516, 519, 617, 618, 714, 716, 814, 815, 817$.  Next, Cristy whispers the leftmost digit in Annie’s ear and then whispers the remaining two digits in Bob’s ear. The following conversation then takes place:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Annie: I don’t know what the number is, but I know Bob doesn’t know too.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bob: At first I didn’t know what the number was, but now I know.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Annie: Ah, then I know the number, too.
From that information, determine Cristy’s number.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(1 vote) Consider a $8\times 8$ grid with light-up squares. In the starting configuration, some subset of the squares are lit up. At each stage, a square lights up if at least two of its immediate neighbors (horizontal or vertical) were “on” during the previous stage. It’s easy to see that for the starting configuration in which eight squares along a diagonal of the board are lit up, the entire board is eventually covered by “on” squares. Several other simple starting configurations with eight “on” squares also result in the entire board being covered. Is it possible for a starting configuration with fewer than eight squares to cover the entire board? If yes, find it; if no, give a proof.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(1 vote) Suppose we draw $n$ distinct lines in the plane that have the maximum number of unique intersections. How many intersections are there?  The resulting configuration partitions the plane into disjoint regions (some of which are polygons with finite area and some are not).  Suppose we color each of the regions so that no two adjacent regions (i.e., share a common edge) have the same color.  What is the fewest colors we could use to accomplish this?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(1 vote) The Infinite Hotel has rooms numbered $1,2,3,4,\ldots$. Every room in the Infinite Hotel is currently occupied.  Is it possible to make room for one more guest (assuming they want a room all to themselves)?  An infinite number of new guests, say $g_1, g_2,g_3,\ldots$, show up in the lobby and each demands a room.  Is it possible to make room for all the new guests even in the hotel is already full? The full infinite bus brings new guests to the full infinite hotel. How can they stay at the hotel?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(1 vote) What size rectangles can be tiled with L-shaped trominoes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A while back I wrote a similar post that highlighted &lt;a href=&quot;https://dcernst.github.io/fifteen-fun-problems/&quot;&gt;15 fun problems&lt;/a&gt; from the first time I taught the course.  You’ll notice that there is some overlap between the two lists.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dana Ernst</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="problem solving" /><category term="math" /><category term="mathematics" /><summary type="html">A few semesters ago we launched a course for mathematics majors, called MAT 220: Introduction to Mathematical Reasoning. The focus of the course is on reasoning and communication through problem solving and written mathematical arguments in order to provide students with more experience and training early in their university studies. The goal is for the students to work on interesting yet challenging multi-step problems that require almost zero background knowledge. The hope is that students will develop (or at least move in the direction of) the habits of mind of a mathematician. The problem solving of the type in this course is a fundamental component of mathematics that receives little focused attention elsewhere in most mathematics programs. I love teaching this course!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Registration for the 2017 SUnMaRC now open</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sunmarc-2017-open/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Registration for the 2017 SUnMaRC now open" /><published>2017-02-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-02-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sunmarc-2017-registration-open</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sunmarc-2017-open/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/SUnMaRCLogoLarge.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-rounded&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; img=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 10px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Registration for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://naumathstat.github.io/sunmarc2017/&quot;&gt;2017 Southwestern Undergraduate Mathematics Research Conference&lt;/a&gt; (aka SUnMaRC) is now open!  &lt;a href=&quot;http://nau.edu&quot;&gt;Northern Arizona University&lt;/a&gt; is hosting this year’s conference on March 31-April 2, 2017.  We are excited to announce Kathryn Bryant (Colorado College), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.segerman.org&quot;&gt;Henry Segerman&lt;/a&gt; (Oklahoma State University), and Steve Wilson (NAU, emeritus) as our &lt;a href=&quot;https://naumathstat.github.io/sunmarc2017/speakers/&quot;&gt;invited speakers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the conference is to welcome undergraduates to the wonderful world of mathematics research, to develop and foster a rich social network between the mathematics students and faculty throughout the great Southwest, and to celebrate the accomplishments of our undergraduate students. We encourage undergraduate students from all years of study to participate and give presentations in any area of mathematics, including applications to other disciplines.  However, while we do recommend giving a talk, it is not a requirement for conference participation. To register for the conference and to submit a title and abstract for a student presentation, visit the &lt;a href=&quot;https://naumathstat.github.io/sunmarc2017/registration/&quot;&gt;2017 SunMaRC Registration page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference began in 2004 as the Arizona Mathematics Undergraduate Conference.  In 2008, the conference changed to SUnMaRC to recognize the participation of institutions throughout the southwest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions about this year’s SUnMaRC, please contact one of the conference organizers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jeffrey.rushall@nau.edu&quot;&gt;Jeff Rushall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:dana.ernst@nau.edu&quot;&gt;Dana Ernst&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Nellie.Gopaul@nau.edu&quot;&gt;Nellie Gopaul&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Tiffany.Lenhart@nau.edu&quot;&gt;Tiffany Lenhart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Dana Ernst</name></author><category term="SUnMaRC" /><category term="undergraduate research" /><category term="math" /><category term="mathematics" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Mathematics Genealogy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/my-mathematics-genealogy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Mathematics Genealogy" /><published>2017-01-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-01-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/my-mathematics-genealogy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/my-mathematics-genealogy/">&lt;p&gt;The mission of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genealogy.math.ndsu.nodak.edu/index.php&quot;&gt;Mathematics Genealogy Project&lt;/a&gt; (MGP) is to compile information about all  mathematicians, living and dead, to create family trees based on advisor-student relationships. The MGP database contains over 200,000 entries.  A complete entry for a mathematician in the database lists the mathematician’s name, year and title of their dissertation, graduating institution, list of their PhD students, and their PhD advisor(s).  Occasionally, some of this information is missing.  You can find my record &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genealogy.math.ndsu.nodak.edu/id.php?id=125763&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Since finishing my PhD in 2008, I’ve poked around the MGP and always thought it would be cool to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genealogy.math.ndsu.nodak.edu/posters.php&quot;&gt;get a poster made&lt;/a&gt; that displays my mathematical genealogy, but I just haven’t gotten around to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my former students, Andrew Lebovitz, recently posted a link on Facebook to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/news/majority-of-mathematicians-hail-from-just-24-scientific-families-1.20491#/b1&quot;&gt;Nature article&lt;/a&gt; that summarizes a paper, titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://epjdatascience.springeropen.com/articles/10.1140/epjds/s13688-016-0088-y&quot;&gt;The classical origin of modern mathematics&lt;/a&gt;, which completed a comprehensive analysis of the MGP database.  One of the interesting findings was that the individuals in the database fall into 84 distinct family trees with two-thirds of the world’s mathematicians concentrated in just 24 of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reading the Nature article, I was motivated to see if I could figure out whether I belonged to one of the 24 families. It wasn’t obvious to me how I would do this without manually clicking on my advisor (&lt;a href=&quot;https://math.colorado.edu/~rmg/&quot;&gt;Richard M. Green&lt;/a&gt;), then my advisor’s advisor, etc. This was slightly more complicated than I expected because there were quite a few ancestors with 2 advisors, so I had to navigate down multiple paths.   As I clicked around, I drew out my family tree in a notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what I discovered.  My longest branch goes back to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genealogy.math.ndsu.nodak.edu/id.php?id=136514&quot;&gt;Nicolo Fontana Tartaglia&lt;/a&gt; (currently 14,428 descendants).  My tree includes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genealogy.math.ndsu.nodak.edu/id.php?id=74313&quot;&gt;Isaac Newton&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genealogy.math.ndsu.nodak.edu/id.php?id=134975&quot;&gt;Galileo Galilei&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genealogy.math.ndsu.nodak.edu/id.php?id=125434&quot;&gt;Marin Mersenne&lt;/a&gt; (who &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mersenne_prime&quot;&gt;Mersenne primes&lt;/a&gt; were named after). Interestingly, no one on this path belongs to one of the 24 families mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;http://epjdatascience.springeropen.com/articles/10.1140/epjds/s13688-016-0088-y&quot;&gt;The classical origin of modern mathematics&lt;/a&gt;.  Also, I was disappointed to find out that I wasn’t related to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genealogy.math.ndsu.nodak.edu/id.php?id=38586&quot;&gt;Leonhard Euler&lt;/a&gt;. However, I am a descendant of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genealogy.math.ndsu.nodak.edu/id.php?id=129422&quot;&gt;Henry Bracken&lt;/a&gt;, who is the head of one of the 24 families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I posted some of this information on Facebook and asked if anyone knew how to automatically create a nice visualization of the directed graph corresponding to my family tree. &lt;a href=&quot;https://math.depaul.edu/cdrupies/&quot;&gt;Chris Drupieski&lt;/a&gt; replied and pointed out a program called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.davidalber.net/geneagrapher/&quot;&gt;Geneagrapher&lt;/a&gt;, which was built to do exactly what I was looking for. In particular, Geneagrapher gathers information for building math genealogy trees from the MGP, which is then stored in dot file format. This data can then be passed to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.graphviz.org&quot;&gt;Graphviz&lt;/a&gt; to generate a directed graph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the steps that I completed to get Geneagrapher up and running on my computer running MacOS 10.11.  The Geneagrapher website suggests using &lt;code&gt;easy_install&lt;/code&gt; via Terminal, but this didn’t immediately work for me.  It often seems that doing anything with Python on my Mac requires a few extra steps.  After doing a little searching around, I found a &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/6012246/why-is-python-easy-install-not-working-on-my-mac&quot;&gt;post on Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt; that solved my issue.  At the command line, I typed the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo chown -R &amp;lt;your_user&amp;gt;:wheel /Library/Python/2.7/site-packages/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you should replace &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;your_user&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; with your username.  Note that using &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; requires you to enter your password.  Next, I installed Geneagrapher using the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;easy_install http://www.davidalber.net/dist/geneagrapher/Geneagrapher-0.2.1-r2.tar.gz&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to use Geneagrapher, you need to input a record number from MGP.  Mine is 125763.  At the command line, I typed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ggrapher -f ernst.dot -a 125763&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can replace &lt;code&gt;ernst&lt;/code&gt; with whatever you’d like the output file to be called. The next step is to pass the dot file to Graphviz.  If you don’t already have Graphviz installed, you can do so using &lt;a href=&quot;http://brew.sh&quot;&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt; (which is also easy to install):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;brew install graphviz&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the Geneagrapher instructions, I typed the following to generate my family tree:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;dot -Tpng ernst.dot &amp;gt; ernst.png&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it is worth mentioning that unless you specify otherwise, the dot and png files will be stored in your home directory.  Below is my mathematical family tree created using Geneagrapher. As you can see, it took a while for my ancestors to leave the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cam.ac.uk&quot;&gt;University of Cambridge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/FamilyTree.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; img=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 10px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dana Ernst</name></author><category term="genealogy" /><category term="math" /><category term="mathematics" /><summary type="html">The mission of the Mathematics Genealogy Project (MGP) is to compile information about all mathematicians, living and dead, to create family trees based on advisor-student relationships. The MGP database contains over 200,000 entries. A complete entry for a mathematician in the database lists the mathematician’s name, year and title of their dissertation, graduating institution, list of their PhD students, and their PhD advisor(s). Occasionally, some of this information is missing. You can find my record here. Since finishing my PhD in 2008, I’ve poked around the MGP and always thought it would be cool to get a poster made that displays my mathematical genealogy, but I just haven’t gotten around to it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fifteen fun problems</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/fifteen-fun-problems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fifteen fun problems" /><published>2016-09-29T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-09-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/fifteen-fun-problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/fifteen-fun-problems/">&lt;p&gt;It’s day 4 of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/loveyourmath?src=hash&quot;&gt;#loveyourmath&lt;/a&gt; campaign! One of the things I enjoy about doing mathematics is working on interesting problems that require a bit of creativity and/or cleverness.  I especially like problems that don’t require you to know very much in advance.  A few semesters ago we launched a course for mathematics majors, called &lt;a href=&quot;http://teaching.danaernst.com/mat220s15/&quot;&gt;MAT 220: Introduction to Mathematical Reasoning&lt;/a&gt;, whose main objective is to make students wrestle with exactly the types of problems I love. In particular, the focus of the course is on reasoning and communication through problem solving and written mathematical arguments in order to provide students with more experience and training early in their university studies. The goal is for the students to work on interesting yet challenging multi-step problems that require almost zero background knowledge. The hope is that students will develop (or at least move in the direction of) the habits of mind of a mathematician. The problem solving of the type in this course is a fundamental component of mathematics that receives little focused attention elsewhere in most mathematics programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are 15 problems from the course.  Originally I was only going to list 5, but it was hard enough to only pick 15. I attempted to showcase a variety of problems that utilize different ways of thinking.  I’m intentionally not providing any solutions.  Some of these problems are classics or variations on classics.  Have fun playing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have 10 sticks in my bag. The length of each stick is an integer. No matter which 3 sticks I try to use, I cannot make a triangle out of those sticks. What is the minimum length of the longest stick?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A mouse eats his way through a 3 by 3 by 3 cube of cheese by tunneling through all 27 of the 1 by 1 by 1 sub-cubes. If she starts at one corner and always moves to an uneaten sub cube, can she finish at the center of the cube?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have two strings of pyrotechnic fuse. The strings do not look homogeneous in thickness but both of them have a label saying 4 minutes. So we can assume that it takes 4 minutes to burn through either of these fuses. How can we measure a one minute interval?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Show that in any group of 6 students there are 3 students who know each other or 3 students who do not know each other.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Suppose someone draws 20 random lines in the plane. What is the maximum number of intersections of these lines?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Suppose you have 12 coins, all identical in appearance and weight except for one that is either heavier or lighter than the other 11 coins. What is the minimum number of weighing one must do with a two-pan scale in order to identify the counterfeit?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Suppose you have 9 coins, all identical in appearance and weight except for one that &lt;em&gt;we know is heavier&lt;/em&gt; than the other 8 coins. What is the minimum number of weighing one must do with a two-pan scale in order to identify the counterfeit?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Four prisoners are making plans to escape from jail. Their current plan requires them to cross a narrow bridge in the dark that has no handrail. In order to successfully cross the bridge, they must use a flashlight.  However, they only have a single flashlight.  To complicate matters, at most two people can be on the bridge at the same time.  So, they will need to make multiple trips across the bridge, returning the flashlight back to the first side of the bridge by having someone walk it back.  Unfortunately, they can’t throw the flashlight.  It takes 1, 2, 5, and 10 minutes for prisoner A, prisoner B, prisoner C, and prisoner D to cross the bridge and when two prisoners are walking together with the flashlight, it takes the time of the slower prisoner.  What is the minimum total amount of time it takes all four prisoners to get across the bridge?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How many ways can 110 be written as the sum of 14 different positive integers?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider the following problem. An overfull prison has decided to terminate some prisoners. The jailer comes up with a game for selecting who gets terminated. Here is his scheme. 10 prisoners are to be lined up all facing the same direction. On the back of each prisoner’s head, the jailer places either a black or a red dot. Each prisoner can only see the color of the dot for all of the prisoners in front of them and the prisoners do not know how many of each color there are. The jailer may use all black dots, or perhaps he uses 3 red and 7 black, but the prisoners do not know. The jailer tells the prisoners that if a prisoner can guess the color of the dot on the back of their head, they will live, but if they guess incorrectly, they will be terminated. The jailer will call on them in order starting at the back of the line. Before lining up the prisoners and placing the dots, the jailer allows the prisoners 5 minutes to come up with a plan that will maximize their survival. What plan can the prisoners devise that will maximize the number of prisoners that survive? Some more info: each prisoner can hear the answer of the prisoner behind them and they will know whether the prisoner behind them has lived or died. Also, each prisoner can only respond with the word “black” or “red.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the senate of the Klingon home world no senator has more than three enemies. Show that the senate can be separated into two houses so that nobody has more than one enemy in the same house.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;100 prisoners are isolated in individual jail cells with no way to communicate. They are currently serving life sentences.  Due to an overcrowded prison, the jailer decides to offer the prisoners the following deal. There is a a room with nothing in it except a light switch (that starts in the off position). At random, the jailer will escort a single prisoner into the room with the light switch. After 5 seconds, the jailer will escort the prisoner back to his/her jail cell. The jailer will repeat this over and over again.  He tells each of the prisoners that if one of the prisoners can indicate when every prisoner has been in the room with the light switch at least once, he will let all the prisoners go.  However, if a prisoner erroneously states that each prisoner has been in the room with the light switch, then all the prisoners will be executed.  Before beginning, the jailer gets all 100 prisoners together and gives them 5 minutes to come up with a plan.  What should their plan be?  It’s important to note that the jailer is choosing prisoners at random to take in the room.  That is, by chance, the same prisoner may be escorted to the room several times in a row.  Also, your task is to devise a scheme for the prisoners to communicate with the light switch.  You shouldn’t bother searching for other ways for the prisoners to communicate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Three boxes, one with black, one with white, and one with black and white balls.  Each of the boxes is labeled B, W, and BW, but unfortunately, &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the boxes are labeled incorrectly.  Moreover, you cannot see inside each of the boxes, but you can reach in and pull a ball out.  What is the minimum number of balls that need to be pulled before you can relabel all the boxes correctly?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imagine you have 25 pebbles, each occupying one square on a 5 by 5 chess board. Suppose that each pebble must move to an adjacent square by only moving up, down, left, or right. Is it possible to do this if every pebble must move and each square is only occupied by a single pebble after all pebbles have moved?  If so, find a solution.  If not, explain why.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Show that in any set of seven different positive integers there are three numbers such that the greatest common divisor of any two of them leaves the same remainder when divided by three.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to see more problems from the course, go &lt;a href=&quot;http://teaching.danaernst.com/files/spring2015/mat220/220ProblemCollection.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt; The &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/loveyourmath?src=hash&quot;&gt;#loveyourmath&lt;/a&gt; 5-day campaign is sponsored by the &lt;a href=&quot;http:maa.org&quot;&gt;Mathematical Association of America&lt;/a&gt;.  The goal of the campaign is to engage a general audience across a broad representation of mathematics, whether it is biology, patterns, textbooks, art, or puzzles.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dana Ernst</name></author><category term="math" /><category term="mathematics" /><category term="problem solving" /><category term="loveyourmath" /><summary type="html">It’s day 4 of the #loveyourmath campaign! One of the things I enjoy about doing mathematics is working on interesting problems that require a bit of creativity and/or cleverness. I especially like problems that don’t require you to know very much in advance. A few semesters ago we launched a course for mathematics majors, called MAT 220: Introduction to Mathematical Reasoning, whose main objective is to make students wrestle with exactly the types of problems I love. In particular, the focus of the course is on reasoning and communication through problem solving and written mathematical arguments in order to provide students with more experience and training early in their university studies. The goal is for the students to work on interesting yet challenging multi-step problems that require almost zero background knowledge. The hope is that students will develop (or at least move in the direction of) the habits of mind of a mathematician. The problem solving of the type in this course is a fundamental component of mathematics that receives little focused attention elsewhere in most mathematics programs.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The 5 groups of order 8</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-5-groups-of-order-8/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 5 groups of order 8" /><published>2016-09-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-09-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the-5-groups-of-order-8</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-5-groups-of-order-8/">&lt;p&gt;It’s day 3 of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/loveyourmath?src=hash&quot;&gt;#loveyourmath&lt;/a&gt; campaign!  For this post, I wanted to share some pictures of some quilts that one of my former students made for me when I was at &lt;a href=&quot;http://plymouth.edu&quot;&gt;Plymouth State University&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that up to isomorphism, there are exactly 5 groups of order 8.  Below are representatives from each isomorphism class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$\mathbb{Z}_8$ (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyclic_group&quot;&gt;cyclic group&lt;/a&gt; of order 8)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$\mathbb{Z}_4\times \mathbb{Z}_2$&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$\mathbb{Z}_2\times \mathbb{Z}_2\times \mathbb{Z}_2$&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$D_4$ (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dihedral_group&quot;&gt;dihedral group&lt;/a&gt; of order 8)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$Q_8$ (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quaternion_group&quot;&gt;quaternion group&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first three groups listed above are abelian while the last two are not.  It’s a fairly straightforward exercise to prove that none of these groups are isomorphic to each other.  It’s a bit more work to prove that the list is complete.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finitely_generated_abelian_group#Classification&quot;&gt;The Fundamental Theorem of Finitely Generated Abelian Groups&lt;/a&gt; guarantees that we haven’t omitted any abelian groups of order 8.  Handling the non-abelian case is trickier.  If you want to know more about to prove that the classification above is correct, check out the Mathematics Stack Exchange post &lt;a href=&quot;http://math.stackexchange.com/questions/64406/how-can-you-show-there-are-only-2-nonabelian-groups-of-order-8&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://groupprops.subwiki.org/wiki/Main_Page&quot;&gt;GroupProps &lt;/a&gt; wiki page about &lt;a href=&quot;http://groupprops.subwiki.org/wiki/Groups_of_order_8&quot;&gt;groups of order 8&lt;/a&gt;, and the nice classification of all groups of order less or equal to 8 that is located &lt;a href=&quot;http://www2.lawrence.edu/fast/corrys/Math300/8Groups.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since groups have binary operations at their core, we can represent a finite group using a table, called a group table.  In order to help out minds recognize patterns in the table, we can color the entries in the table according to which group element occurs.  Of course, if we rearrange the column and row headings of the table, we have to rearrange or recolor the entries of the table accordingly.  Doing so may make some patterns more or less visually recognizable.  Similar to the book &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.bentley.edu/empl/c/ncarter/vgt/&quot;&gt;Visual Group Theory&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.bentley.edu/empl/c/ncarter/&quot;&gt;Nathan Carter&lt;/a&gt; (Bentley University), I utilize colored group tables in several chapters of &lt;a href=&quot;http://dcernst.github.io/IBL-AbstractAlgebra/&quot;&gt;An Inquiry-Based Approach to Abstract Algebra&lt;/a&gt;, which is an open-source abstract algebra book that I wrote to be used with an &lt;a href=&quot;http://maamathedmatters.blogspot.com/2013/05/what-heck-is-ibl.html&quot;&gt;IBL approach&lt;/a&gt; to the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was teaching out of Carter’s book during the summer of 2009, one of my students (Michelle Reagan) made five quilts that correspond to colored group tables for the five groups of order 8.  Here are pictures of the quilts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Quilt1.JPG&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; img=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 15px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Quilt2.JPG&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; img=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 15px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Quilt3.JPG&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; img=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 15px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Quilt4.JPG&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; img=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 15px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Quilt5.JPG&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; img=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 15px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a fun exercise to figure out which quilt corresponds to which group.  I’ll leave it to you to think about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt; The &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/loveyourmath?src=hash&quot;&gt;#loveyourmath&lt;/a&gt; 5-day campaign is sponsored by the &lt;a href=&quot;http:maa.org&quot;&gt;Mathematical Association of America&lt;/a&gt;.  The goal of the campaign is to engage a general audience across a broad representation of mathematics, whether it is biology, patterns, textbooks, art, or puzzles.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dana Ernst</name></author><category term="math" /><category term="mathematics" /><category term="book" /><category term="group theory" /><category term="abstract algebra" /><category term="loveyourmath" /><summary type="html">It’s day 3 of the #loveyourmath campaign! For this post, I wanted to share some pictures of some quilts that one of my former students made for me when I was at Plymouth State University.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A (new) favorite math book</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/a-new-favorite-math-book/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A (new) favorite math book" /><published>2016-09-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-09-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/a-new-favorite-math-book</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/a-new-favorite-math-book/">&lt;p&gt;As part of day two of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/loveyourmath?src=hash&quot;&gt;#loveyourmath&lt;/a&gt; campaign, I wanted to share a math book that has recently become one of my favorites, namely &lt;a href=&quot;http://math.depaul.edu/tpeter21/Eulerian.html&quot;&gt;Eulerian Numbers&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;http://math.depaul.edu/tpeter21/index.html&quot;&gt;T. Kyle Petersen&lt;/a&gt; (DePaul University). The book was published in late 2015.  According &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.springer.com/us/book/9781493930906&quot;&gt;Springer&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This text presents the Eulerian numbers in the context of modern enumerative, algebraic, and geometric combinatorics. The book first studies Eulerian numbers from a purely combinatorial point of view, then embarks on a tour of how these numbers arise in the study of hyperplane arrangements, polytopes, and simplicial complexes. Some topics include a thorough discussion of gamma-nonnegativity and real-rootedness for Eulerian polynomials, as well as the weak order and the shard intersection order of the symmetric group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book also includes a parallel story of Catalan combinatorics, wherein the Eulerian numbers are replaced with Narayana numbers. Again there is a progression from combinatorics to geometry, including discussion of the associahedron and the lattice of noncrossing partitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final chapters discuss how both the Eulerian and Narayana numbers have analogues in any finite Coxeter group, with many of the same enumerative and geometric properties. There are four supplemental chapters throughout, which survey more advanced topics, including some open problems in combinatorial topology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This textbook will serve a resource for experts in the field as well as for graduate students and others hoping to learn about these topics for the first time.​&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, most of my research in pure mathematics falls in the category of algebraic combinatorics.  However, I’ve had very little formal training in combinatorics.  It turns out that I know quite a bit about Catalan combinatorics, but again, it’s not a subject that I’ve explicitly studied.  Prior to opening the book, I knew next to nothing about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eulerian_number&quot;&gt;Eulerian numbers&lt;/a&gt;, let alone &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Narayana_number&quot;&gt;Narayana numbers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/EulerianNumbers.jpg&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; img=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;margin-right: 15px&quot; /&gt; Right around the time I found out I would be teaching our graduate combinatorics class during the Fall 2016 semester, I learned about Kyle’s book.  I was really looking forward to teaching the class because I figured that one of the best ways to fill in my lack of formal training in combinatorics was to teach a class about it.  After thumbing through Kyle’s book (and thinking, “wow, I don’t really know any of this stuff!”), I decided that I could run the class as a sort of “topics course” focusing on Eulerian numbers and Catalan combinatorics while hitting many of the core ideas of enumerative combinatorics along the way.  As a bonus, I would be forced to learn lots of cool things that relate to my research interests, many of which I probably should have know more about anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m currently in week 5 of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://dcernst.github.io/teaching/mat526f16/&quot;&gt;Topics in Combinatorics&lt;/a&gt; graduate course in which we are closely following Kyle’s book.  Despite the fact that we’ve barely covered two chapters, I’m absolutely in love with the book and the content.  It’s so much fun!  I have to admit that I don’t always know which specific topics are key ideas and which are just fun side stories, but I think that’s mostly true every time one teaches a course for the first time. One of the things I really like about the themes in the book is that connects with cutting edge research topics.  We’re learning about “current events” in algebraic/enumerative combinatorics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My only minor complaint is that I wish Kyle provided less detail in the hints/solutions for the exercises in the back of the book.  On the other hand, there have been a couple times where I’ve thought, “geez, there’s no way I would have ever come up with that argument without significant guidance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt; The &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/loveyourmath?src=hash&quot;&gt;#loveyourmath&lt;/a&gt; 5-day campaign is sponsored by the &lt;a href=&quot;http:maa.org&quot;&gt;Mathematical Association of America&lt;/a&gt;.  The goal of the campaign is to engage a general audience across a broad representation of mathematics, whether it is biology, patterns, textbooks, art, or puzzles.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dana Ernst</name></author><category term="math" /><category term="mathematics" /><category term="book" /><category term="Kyle Petersen" /><category term="loveyourmath" /><summary type="html">As part of day two of the #loveyourmath campaign, I wanted to share a math book that has recently become one of my favorites, namely Eulerian Numbers by T. Kyle Petersen (DePaul University). The book was published in late 2015. According Springer:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How did I become a mathematician?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2016-09-26-how-did-i-become-a-mathematician/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How did I become a mathematician?" /><published>2016-09-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-09-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-did-i-become-a-mathematician</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2016-09-26-how-did-i-become-a-mathematician/">&lt;p&gt;Today is day one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/loveyourmath?src=hash&quot;&gt;#loveyourmath&lt;/a&gt; 5-day campaign sponsored by the &lt;a href=&quot;http:maa.org&quot;&gt;Mathematical Association of America&lt;/a&gt;.  The goal of the campaign is to engage a general audience across a broad representation of mathematics, whether it is biology, patterns, textbooks, art, or puzzles.  One of the potential topics for day one is to share what inspired you to get into mathematics, which is something I’ve been meaning to write about for a while.  Here goes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love mathematics.  However, I have not always felt this way.  As a child, I was okay at mathematics but far from exceptional (and this is still true!).  At some point during my youth, I developed a distaste for the subject.  Perhaps more than most young children, the one question I obsessively asked over and over again was “why?”  I could not stop my mind from inquiring into the nature of things.  The one place that my incessant questioning was met with resistance was in math class, where the response was usually something like, “don’t ask why,” “that’s just the way it is,” or “just accept it.”  After hearing this a few hundred times, I started to accept that mathematics was just a bunch of rules that needed to be memorized.  This attitude lasted throughout high school and into my freshman year in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After graduating high school in 1993, I accepted an academic scholarship to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.gmu.edu&quot;&gt;George Mason University&lt;/a&gt; in Fairfax, Virginia.  Like most freshman, I had no idea what I wanted to do with my life, and I certainly did not think I would major in mathematics, let alone pursue a career in mathematics.  Not being fond of writing papers at that time, I began contemplating majors that would require the least amount of writing.  I figured that I would major in one of the sciences and upon thumbing through the academic catalog, I soon realized that regardless of which one I chose, I would have to take calculus.  So, I registered for Calculus I in the fall semester of my sophomore year, which I did not take in high school. My plan was to “just get it out of the way.”  As it turns out, this class changed my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this first day of class, I walked into a rather large lecture hall.  Much to my disliking, my class had well over a hundred students in it.  I promptly sat in the very back of the room.  Soon thereafter, in walked &lt;a href=&quot;http://math.gmu.edu/faculty_staff/sachs.htm&quot;&gt;Dr. Robert Sachs&lt;/a&gt;.  I remember thinking to myself that if you looked up “math geek” in the dictionary, you might see a picture of my new math professor.  I’m not sure when it happened, but at some point during the semester, I went from going through the motions (while doing quite well) to being completely captivated during each lecture.  This math class was unlike any I had ever had.  For the first time, I had a teacher, who not only understood mathematics, but attempted to explain why it works the way that it does.  Someone was finally answering my “why” questions! Even more importantly, Dr. Sachs was teaching me that I could discover the answers to all of my questions independently, and that something wonderful can be gained in the process.  As a student in the class, I no longer felt like the sole purpose of being there was to quickly jot down a recipe for solving a few meaningless problems.  Collectively, we were on a journey of discovery and along the way I was encouraged to turn over as many rocks as I could to see what lived beneath. Just about anyone can write facts on the blackboard, but Dr. Sachs has a gift that allows him to teach effectively while conveying the beauty of mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following semester, I made sure that I registered for Calculus II with Dr. Sachs.  Yet, despite my budding interest in mathematics, I still had not even remotely considered majoring in the subject.  I was a jock, not a math geek.  Sometime around the middle of the semester, Dr. Sachs was returning exams and after personally handing me my exam at the back of the room, he asked me what my major was, and I probably just shrugged my shoulders.  I can say with absolute certainty that I would not be where I am today if he hadn’t responded with, “you should major in mathematics.”  This was not the last time he made this suggestion, as I took some convincing, but eventually I was won over.  He saw in me, as I am sure he has for many students, a potential that I did not know I possessed. Eventually, I declared mathematics as my major, which I don’t think anyone would have predicted a few years earlier.  Dr. Sachs permanently changed the trajectory of my life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a short-lived start to a master’s degree in education, I went on to receive a master’s degree in mathematics from &lt;a href=&quot;http://nau.edu&quot;&gt;Northern Arizona University&lt;/a&gt;, and after a couple years of teaching at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.frontrange.edu&quot;&gt;Front Range Community College&lt;/a&gt; in Colorado, I returned to graduate school and completed my PhD at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://colorado.edu&quot;&gt;University of Colorado Boulder&lt;/a&gt;.  I currently cannot imagine myself being anything other than a mathematician and a teacher, but unlike many of my colleagues, I was a late bloomer, so to speak.  I certainly didn’t aspire to be professor of mathematics when I was a child.  I do have vague memories of wanting to be a photographer for National Geographic or a deep ocean explorer.  In fact, I think I lucked out as being a mathematician has more in common with these two than the average person might suspect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I readily admit that I am peculiar, my path from despising mathematics to loving the subject has given me a perspective that many mathematicians likely do not have as most of them either excelled at mathematics, had an interest in the subject from a very early age, or both.  This perspective has played a fundamental role in my teaching and has helped me relate to my students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I don’t think Bob looks like a math geek anymore.  It’s been a lot of fun to hang out with him at conferences and get to know each other as teachers and mathematicians.  Thanks Bob!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dana Ernst</name></author><category term="math" /><category term="mathematics" /><category term="Bob Sachs" /><category term="loveyourmath" /><summary type="html">Today is day one of the #loveyourmath 5-day campaign sponsored by the Mathematical Association of America. The goal of the campaign is to engage a general audience across a broad representation of mathematics, whether it is biology, patterns, textbooks, art, or puzzles. One of the potential topics for day one is to share what inspired you to get into mathematics, which is something I’ve been meaning to write about for a while. Here goes!</summary></entry></feed>